Okay, in this video we are going to be
discussing the estimating methods,
right, cost management, estimating
methods.
Now, these estimating methods were
actually covered in a prior video,
right, in schedule management.
And in fact, the same estimating methods
that we talked about in schedule
management for both
predictive and agile would
be relevant here as
well in cost management.
And in fact, schedule and cost management
are both very similar to one another.
They both go hand in hand.
I mean, let's think about this.
Your schedule has a direct impact on your
cost.
If you need to extend your schedule, that's
going to have an impact on your cost.
And vice versa.
Your cost and your budget
can have a direct impact
on your schedule and
your timeline on your project.
They both interact with the one another.
And both schedule and cost are major
constraints on a project.
Right?
So it more than makes sense then.
that the tools that we talked about or the
estimating methods that we talked about in
schedule management would be relevant here
as well in cost management.
And so the ones that's listed here are the
predictive, right, but it refers to both.
Both predictive and agile, the estimating
methods that we talked about in schedule
management would be relevant here as well
in cost management.
So let's go through some of
these predictive ones then,
these predictive estimating
method, just a summary.
So, analogous estimating.
Remember, analogous estimating is
comparing to historical information.
We've done this kind of project before, or
someone else has done
this kind of project before.
And so now we're using this to come up
with a high-level estimate of,
you know, how much we think this project
is going to cost.
Whereas in the previous video,
when we were talking about schedule,
right, it was looking
at, well, last time we
did this work, it took
this much time, right?
They don't know how long will it take us
now?
In this case, we're talking about the
cost.
Last time we did this piece of work or
last time someone did this activity,
it cost this much, right?
So there's our analogous estimate.
So it's a very simple example.
Again, let's stick to the theme of
building a house.
So let's say, you know, we know that one
of our neighbors installed a sunroom.
And it cost them, you know, $15,000.
Let's just say, $15,000 to install this
sunroom.
So there's our analogous estimate.
We have a very similar house and we want
to install a very similar sunroom.
So our neighbors, it cost them $15,000.
So there's our analogous estimate.
So the advantage with analogous estimating
is quick and easy.
But it's a high level ballpark figure.
It's not going to be very accurate.
So just because it costs
them $15,000 doesn't
necessarily mean it's
going to cost us $15,000.
So that's the advantage and disadvantage
then of analogous.
And advantages, it's quick and easy,
disadvantage, not very accurate.
But it's a high-level ballpark figure.
Then there's parametric estimating.
It's parametric estimating.
It's using first principal mathematics,
right?
A statistical relationship or using rules
and algorithms.
extrapolate results.
And so is a very simple example.
We want to install flooring.
This flooring costs $5 a square foot,
and we have 100 square feet.
So how much is that going to cost?
$500.
So you're always doing some kind of math.
So the advantage of what's
parametric is, generally,
it's going to be more
accurate than an algus, right?
Because we're using some kind of math,
right?
We're using rules and algorithms to
extrapolate results.
But the disadvantage is that in some
situation, the parameters will not scale,
or the parameters might not scale.
So, for example, then, if it
costs us $1 to buy one bottle of
water, how much will it cost
to buy 1,000 bottles of water?
Well, if you do the math, you're going to
come up with $1,000.
Well, just because it costs
$1 to buy one bottle of water,
you're not going to spend
$1,000 and 1,000 bottles of water.
So straight parametric estimating then is
not going to take into consideration
things like learning curves, economies of
scale, and so on and so forth.
Discounts in this case.
It doesn't take into consideration that.
It's straight parametric estimating.
So that can be the disadvantage of
parametric.
The advantage is generally
it's going to be more accurate
because you're using
rules and algorithms, right?
But the disadvantage
is, in certain situations,
those parameters don't always scale.
Then you have bottom-up
estimating and a bottom-up
estimate is a very,
very detailed estimate.
You're taking your activities,
you're doing a detailed analysis,
further breaking it down into little
sub-activities, and then
aggregating the total.
And then another part of bottom-up
estimating is you're rolling up each layer
of the work breakdown
structure in order to get to
the final cost or the final
budget for your project.
And then you have 3 point estimating.
And we have a completely separate video on
3 point estimating.
And 3 point estimating then, remember
there's two types.
You've got the triangular distribution and
the beta distribution.
More than likely, if they're
asking you a question on the
exam, it will be the beta
distribution, which is the pert.
And remember, you have the pert formula,
optimistic, plus four times, most likely,
plus pessimistic divided by 6.
And then make sure you remember those
standard deviation formulas as well.
And so, as I said, there's a separate
video on those, right?
So make sure then you do understand those
formulas.
Our videos that we had was
from a schedule perspective,
but the exact same
principles apply to cost.
So instead of using days or weeks,
we're going to use dollars.
That's the only difference.
Now, a couple of additional ranges that
you need to be aware of, and this is in
addition to the 6 sigma
ranges, the 2 sigma, 3 sigma
ranges, these are a
couple of additional ranges.
So the first one here, then, is something
called a rough order of magnitude,
or a ROM, rough order of magnitude.
And a rough order of magnitude is in the
range of minus 25 to plus 75%.
minus 25 to plus 75%.
So make sure you know that.
I mean, you could get asked some direct
questions on that.
What is a rough order of magnitude range
on an estimate of $100,000?
Well, it's minus 25%, which is 75,000 to
plus 75%, which is 175,000.
So there's your rough order of magnitude,
75 to 175,000.
Now, that's a big range.
That is a really big range.
But that's why it's called a rough order
of magnitude.
And you use a rough order of magnitude at
the initiating, initiating phase of a
project or the initiating of a process,
or the initiating of an activity.
We don't have any details yet.
We don't have a lot of details.
We just have some very, very high-level
figures.
and so that's what the ruff order of
magnitude is.
And, you know, just think of it as very,
very high level.
That's where, I mean,
and you can see, you know,
minus 75 to plus 75%,
it's a very, very wide range.
So you're going to use a rough order of
magnitude right at the beginning of an
activity, beginning of a project,
and so and so forth.
When you're well into your planning,
you should be a definitive estimate.
And a definitive estimate is minus 5 to
plus 10%.
Right.
So now, these are PMI's standards.
Every industry, every organisation is
going to have their own definition of what
they consider a rough order of magnitude
and a definitive estimate.
So just for the exam
purposes, PMP exam purposes,
rough order of magnitude
is minus 25 to plus 75%.
Definitive minus 5 to plus 10%.
And that should be when you're well into
your planet.
A definitive should be when you're well
into your planning.
And of course, remember the term
progressive elaboration.
We're constantly making updates.
As more information is
gathered, we're drilling
down into more and more of the details.
So that's exactly what we're doing here.
You're going to be using different cost
estimates, or are they going to be using
different levels of accuracy throughout
your project.
At the beginning of
the project is going to
be very high level, minus 25 to plus 75%.
And then as you're going
through the project, those
accuracy are going to get
more and more accurate.
until, you know, from PMI's
purposes, they're saying
a definitive estimate will
be minus 5 to plus 10%.